I'd like to start with a short story.
أحب أن أبدأ بقصّة قصيرة.
It's about a little boy
حول طفل صغير
whose father was a history buff
كان والده مولعا بالتاريخ
and who used to take him by the hand
واعتاد أن يقوده من يده
to visit the ruins of an ancient metropolis
لزيارة آثار حاضرة قديمة
on the outskirts of their camp.
توجد في محيط مخيمهم.
They would always stop by to visit
دائما ما كانوا يتوقفون لزيارة
these huge winged bulls that used to guard
الثيران ذات الأجنحة الضخمة التي كانت تحرس
the gates of that ancient metropolis,
بوابات تلك المدينة القديمة،
and the boy used to be scared
والطفل كان خائفا
of these winged bulls,
من هذه الثيران المجنحة،
but at the same time they excited him.
لكنها كانت تثيره في نفس الوقت.
And the dad used to use those bulls
والأب كان يستعمل تلك الثيران
to tell the boy stories about
ليخبر الطفل قصصا حول
that civilization and their work.
تلك الحضارة وأعمالها.
Let's fast-forward to the
دعونا نمرّ عقودا عديدة في المستقبل
San Francisco Bay Area many decades later,
لمنطقة خليج سان فرانسيسكو،
where I started a technology company
حيث أنشأت شركة تقنية
that brought the world its first
جلبت للعالم أوّل
3D laser scanning system.
نظام للمسح اللايزري ثلاثي الأبعاد.
Let me show you how it works.
دعوني أريكم كيف تعمل.
Female Voice: Long range laser scanning
صوت أنثوي: يمسح لايزر ذو نطاق طويل
by sending out a pulse that's a laser beam of light.
عبر إطلاق نبضة تتمثل في شعاع من ضوء اللايزر.
The system measures the beam's time of flight,
يقيس النظام زمن صعود الشعاع،
recording the time it takes for the light
مسجّلا الزمن الذي يستغرقه الضوء
to hit a surface and make its return.
ليصطدم بسطح ويقوم بالرجوع.
With two mirrors, the scanner calculates
يحسب الماسح الضوئي باستعمال مرآتين
the beam's horizontal and vertical angles,
زوايا الشعاع الأفقية والعمودية،
giving accurate x, y, and z coordinates.
مقدّما احداثيات طول وعرض وارتفاع دقيقة.
The point is then recorded
وبالتالي يتم تسجيل النقطة
into a 3D visualization program.
في برنامج للتصوير ثلاثي الأبعاد.
All of this happens in seconds.
ويحدث كل هذا في ثوان.
Ben Kacyra: You can see here,
بان كاسايرا: يمكنكم أن تروا هنا،
these systems are extremely fast.
أن هذه الأنظمة سريعة للغاية.
They collect millions of points at a time
هي تجمع ملايين النقاط في كل مرة
with very high accuracy
بدقة عالية للغاية
and very high resolution.
وبوضوح عالي الشدة
A surveyor with traditional survey tools
وماسح أراضي لديه أدوات مسح تقليدية
would be hard-pressed to produce
سيستخدم بكامل طاقته لينتج
maybe 500 points in a whole day.
500 نقطة ربما خلال يوم بأكمله.
These babies would be producing
هذه الآلات الصغيرة كان بإمكانها إنتاج
something like ten thousand points a second.
شيئ من قبيل عشرة آلاف نقطة في الثانية.
So, as you can imagine,
لذلك، حسبما يمكن أن تتخيل،
this was a paradigm shift
كان هذا تحولا منهجيا
in the survey and construction
في المسح والإنشاء
as well as in reality capture industry.
كذلك في صناعة التقاط الواقع.
Approximately ten years ago,
منذ عشر سنوات تقريبا،
my wife and I started a foundation to do good,
أسست مع زوجتي مؤسسة للقيام بشيء جيد،
and right about that time,
ومحقّ لذلك الوقت،
the magnificent Bamiyan Buddhas,
تمثالا بوذا باميان،
hundred and eighty foot tall in Afghanistan,
في أفغانستان ذو الخمس والخمسين مترا طولا،
were blown up by the Taliban.
تم تفجيرهما من قبل طالبان.
They were gone in an instant.
لقد اختفيا في لحظة.
And unfortunately, there was
وللأسف، لم يكن هناك
no detailed documentation of these Buddhas.
أي توثيق مفصّل لتمثالا بوذا هذان.
This clearly devastated me,
من الجليّ أن ذلك حطمني،
and I couldn't help but wonder about
ولم أستطع القيام بشيئ سوى التساؤل عن
the fate of my old friends, the winged bulls,
مصير الثيران المجنحة أصدقائي القدامى،
and the fate of the many, many
ومصير العديد والعديد من
heritage sites all over the world.
مواقع التراث حول العالم.
Both my wife and I
لقد كنت وزوجتي
were so touched by this
متأثرين للغاية بهذا
that we decided to
لحدّ أننا قررنا أن
expand the mission of our foundation
توسيع مهمة المؤسسة
to include digital heritage preservation
لتشمل الحفاظ الرقمي على تراث
of world sites.
المواقع العالمية.
We called the project CyArk,
وأسمينا المشروع ساي آرك،
which stands for Cyber Archive.
اختصارا لسايبر آركايف (الأرشيف المرقمن).
To date, with the help of
ولغاية اليوم، بمساعدة
a global network of partners,
شبكة عالمية من الشركاء،
we've completed close to fifty projects.
أتممنا ما يقرب من خمسين مشروعا.
Let me show you some of them:
دعوني أعرض لكم بعضا منها:
Chichen Itza,
تشيتشن إيتزا،
Rapa Nui --
رابا نويي --
and what you're seeing here
وما ترونه هنا
are the cloud of points --
هي سحابة من النقاط --
Babylon,
بابل،
Rosslyn Chapel,
كنيسة روسلين،
Pompeii,
بومبيي،
and our latest project, Mt. Rushmore,
ومشروعنا الأخير جبل راشمور،
which happened to be one of
والذي صادف أن كان أحد
our most challenging projects.
أكثر مشاريعنا تحديا.
As you see here, we had to develop
وكما ترون هنا، كان يجب أن نطور
a special rig to bring the scanner
رافعة خاصة لجعل الماسح الضوئي
up close and personal.
قريبا من الأشخاص.
The results of our work in the field
نتائج عملنا الميداني
are used to produce
تُستعمل لإنتاج
media and deliverables to be used
منتجات إعلامية ومخرجات فعلية يستغلها
by conservators and researchers.
القيمون على التراث والباحثون.
We also produce media for
كذلك ننتج منتجات إعلامية
dissemination to the public --
لنشرها للجمهور --
free through the CyArk website.
مجانا عبر موقع ساي آرك.
These would be used for education,
وسيتم استعمالها في التعليم،
cultural tourism, etc.
والسياحة الثقافية، إلخ.
What you're looking at in here
و ما تنظرون إليه هنا
is a 3D viewer that we developed
هو ماسح ثلاثي الأبعاد طورناه
that would allow the display
يسمح بعرض
and manipulation of [the] cloud of points
وتعديل سحابة النقاط
in real time, cutting sections through them
في الزمن الواقعي، قاطعين أجزاء عبر النقاط
and extracting dimensions.
ومستخرجين أبعادها.
This happens to be the cloud of points
ومن المصادفة أن تكون هذه سحابة نقاط
for Tikal.
تيكال. (مدينة أثرية لحضارة المايا)
In here you see a traditional 2D
وهنا ترون تصويرا تقليديا ثنائي الأبعاد
architectural engineering drawing
لرسم هندسي معماري
that's used for preservation, and of course
يُستعمل لحفظ معالم الموقع وطبعا
we tell the stories through fly-throughs.
نروي القصص عبر محاكاة حاسوبية لعملية الطيران فوقه.
And here, this is a fly-through
وهنا محاكاة حاسوبية لعملية طيران فوق الموقع
the cloud of points of Tikal,
وهنا سحابة نقاط موقع تيكال،
and here you see it rendered
وترونها هنا تتولّد
and photo-textured with the photography
وصورتها منسوجة عبر التصوير الفوتغرافي.
that we take of the site.
التي نلتقطها للموقع.
And so this is not a video.
وبالتالي هذا ليس فيديو.
This is actual 3D points with
هذه نقاط حقيقية ثلاثية الأبعاد
two to three millimeter accuracy.
بدقة إثنان إلى ثلاثة ميليميترات.
And of course the data can be used
وبالطبع يمكن أن تُستعمل البيانات
to develop 3D models that are
لتطوير نماذج ثلاثية الأبعاد
very accurate and very detailed.
دقيقة ومفصلة للغاية.
And here you're looking at a model
وتنظرون هنا لنموذج
that's extracted from the cloud of points
اُستخرج من سحابة نقاط
for Stirling Castle.
لقلعة ستيرلينغ.
It's used for studies, for visualization,
يُستعمل في الدراسات والتصوير
as well as for education.
وفي التعليم أيضا.
And finally, we produce mobile apps
وأخيرا ننتج تطبيقات جوال
that include narrated virtual tools.
تضم أدوات إفتراضية تحككي قصصا.
The more I got involved
وكلما توغلت
in the heritage field,
في ميدان التراث
the more it became clear to me
كلما اتضح لي
that we are losing the sites
أننا نخسر المواقع
and the stories faster than we can
والقصص أسرع مما يمكن
physically preserve them.
أن نحافظ عليها ماديا.
Of course, earthquakes
بالطبع، فالزلازل
and all the natural phenomena --
وكل الظواهر الطبيعية --
floods, tornadoes, etc. --
من فياضانات وأعاصير، إلخ. --
take their toll.
تسبب تدميرا.
However, what occurred to me was
لكن ما وضح لي أن
human-caused destruction, which was
التدمير الذي سببه البشر والذي
not only causing a significant portion
لم يسبب فقط جزءا معتبرا
of the destruction, but actually
من التدمير ولكن في الحقيقة
it was accelerating.
إنه يتسارع.
This includes arson,
هذا يشمل الحرق العمد
urban sprawl,
والتوسع العمراني العشوائي
acid rain, not to mention
المطر الحمضي ودون ذكر
terrorism and wars.
الإرهاب والحروب.
It was getting more and more apparent
لقد بدأ يتجلّى شيئا فشيئا
that we're fighting a losing battle.
أننا نخوض معركة خاسرة.
We're losing our sites
إننا نفقد مواقعنا
and the stories,
والقصص
and basically we're losing
ونفقد أساسا
a piece -- and a significant piece --
قطعة -- وقطعة معتبرة --
of our collective memory.
من ذاكرتنا الجمعية.
Imagine us as a human race
تخيل أننا كنوع بشري
not knowing where we came from.
لا نعرف من أين أتينا.
Luckily, in the last two or three decades,
لحسن الحظ، في العقدين إلى الثلاثة عقود السابقة
digital technologies have been developing
تتطور التقنيات الرقمية
that have helped us to develop tools
التي ساعدتنا لتطوير أدوات
that we've brought to bear
جلبناها لتستغل
in the digital preservation,
في الحفظ الرقمي
in our digital preservation war.
في حربنا للحفظ الرقمي.
This includes, for example,
وهي تشمل على سبيل المثال
the 3D laser scanning systems,
أنظمة المسح الليزري ثلاثية الأبعاد
ever more powerful personal computers,
والحواسب الشخصية الأكثر قوة على الإطلاق
3D graphics,
والغرافيك ثلاثي الأبعاد
high-definition digital photography,
والتصوير الفوتوغرافي العالي الدقة
not to mention the Internet.
ناهيك عن الإنترنت.
Because of this accelerated
بسبب تسارع
pace of destruction,
نسق التدمير،
it became clear to us that we needed
اتضح لدينا أن كنا نحتاج
to challenge ourselves and our partners
لتحدي أنفسنا وشركائنا
to accelerate our work.
لتسريع عملنا.
And we created a project
وأنشأنا مشروعا
we call the CyArk 500 Challenge --
نسميه تحدي ساي آرك 500 --
and that is to digitally preserve
ويتمثل في أن نحفظ رقميا
500 World Heritage Sites
500 موقعا للتراث العالمي
in five years.
في خمس سنوات.
We do have the technology
لدينا التقنية
that's scaleable,
التي يمكن مضاعفة جهدها،
and our network of global partners
وشبكتنا من الشركاء العالميين
has been expanding and can be expanded
تتوسع ويمكن أن تتوسع
at a rapid rate,
بنسق سريع،
so we're comfortable
لذلك نحن مطمئنون
that this task can be accomplished.
لإمكانية إنجاز هذه المهمة.
However, to me, the 500 is
لكن بالنسبة لي فإن الخمس مائة هي
really just the first 500.
في الحقيقة الخمس مائة الأولى فقط
In order to sustain our work into the future,
لكي نضمن أن يستمر عملنا في المستقبل
we use technology centers
نستعمل مراكز تقنية
where we partner with
نقوم بشراكة مع
local universities and colleges
الجامعات المحلية والكليات
to take the technology to them,
لنجلب التقنية إليهم.
whereby they then can help us
ليتمكنوا من مساعدتنا
with digital preservation of their heritage sites,
في الحفظ الرقمي لمواقعهم التراثية،
and at the same time, it gives them
وفي الوقت نفسه تعطيهم
the technology to benefit from in the future.
التقنية التي سيستفيدون منها في المستقبل.
Let me close with another short story.
دعوني أختم بقصة قصيرة أخرى.
Two years ago, we were approached
فاتحنا منذ سنتان
by a partner of ours to digitally preserve
شريك لدينا حول الحفظ الرقمي
an important heritage site,
لموقع تراثي مهم،
a UNESCO heritage site in Uganda,
موقع تراث اليونسكو في أوغندا،
the Royal Kasubi Tombs.
مقابر كاسوبي الملكية.
The work was done successfully in the field,
تم القيام بالعمل بنجاح في الميدان
and the data was archived
وتمت أرشفة البيانات
and publicly disseminated
ونشرت للجمهور
through the CyArk website.
من خلال موقع ساي آرك.
Last March,
في مارس الماضي،
we received very sad news.
تلقينا خبرا محزنا جدا.
The Royal Tombs had been destroyed
لقد دُمرت المقابر الملكية
by suspected arson.
عبر حريق متعمد ومُريب.
A few days later, we received a call:
بعد عدة أيام تلقينا مكالمة جاء فيها:
"Is the data available
"هل أن البيانات متوفرة
and can it be used for reconstruction?"
وهل يمكن أن تستعمل لإعادة التشييد؟"
Our answer, of course, was yes.
كان جوابنا، بطبيعة الحال، نعم.
Let me leave you with a final thought.
دعوني أترككم مع فكرة أخيرة.
Our heritage is much more than
تراثنا يفوق كثيرا
our collective memory --
ذاكرتنا الجمعية --
it's our collective treasure.
إنه كنزنا الجماعي.
We owe it to our children,
ندين لأطفالنا
our grandchildren and the generations
ولأحفادنا وللأجيال
we will never meet
التي لن نلتقي بها أبدا
to keep it safe
بأن نبقيه محميا
and to pass it along.
ونمرره لمن بعدنا.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Well, I'm staying here because
حسنا، أنا باق هنا لأننا
we wanted to demonstrate to you
أردنا أن نبرهن لكم
the power of this technology
قوة هذه التقنية
and so, while I've been speaking,
ولذلك عندما كنت أتحدث
you have been scanned.
تم اخضاعكم للمسح الضوئي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The two wizards that I have
العبقريان اللذان لدي
that are behind the curtain
واللذان خلف الستار
will help me bring
سيساعداني على نقل
the results on the screen.
النتائج على الشاشة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is all in 3D and of course
هذا كله بأبعاد ثلاثية وبالطبع
you can fly through the cloud of points.
تستطيع التحليق فوق سحابة النقاط.
You can look at it from on top,
تستطيع أن تنظر إليها من فوق
from the ceiling.
ومن السقف.
You can look from different vantage points,
تستطيع أن تنظر من إطلالات مختلفة،
but I'm going to ask Doug to zoom in
لكن سأسأل داغ ليقرّب
on an individual in the crowd,
لفرد ضمن الحشد،
just to show the amount of detail
لنبين لكم لا غير كمية التفاصيل
that we can create.
التي يمكن أن ننشئها.
So you have been digitally preserved
إذن لقد تمت حفظكم رقميا
in about four minutes.
خلال حوالي أربع دقائق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'd like to thank the wizards here.
أحب أن أشكر العباقرة هنا.
We were very lucky to have
لقد كنا محظوظين جدا لأنه لدينا
two of our partners participate in this:
إثنان من شركائنا يشاركان في هذا:
the Historic Scotland,
هيستورك سكوتلاند
and the Glasgow School of Art.
وكلية غلاسغو للفن.
I'd like to also thank personally
وأريد أيضا أن أشكر شخصيا
the efforts of David Mitchell,
جهود ديفيد ميتشل
who is the Director of Conservation
والذي هو مدير الحفاظ
at Historic Scotland.
لدى هيستورك سكوتلاند.
David.
ديفيد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And Doug Pritchard, who's the Head of
وداغ بريتشارد والذي هو مسؤول
Visualization at the Glasgow School of Art.
التصوير لدى كلية غلاسغو للفن.
Let's give them a hand.
لنصفّق لهم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا.